Register of the Poland. Ambasada (Soviet Union) records, 1941-1944
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ambasada (Soviet Union) records
1941-1944
45014
Hoover Institution Archives
58 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize folder (24.6 linear feet)
Reports, correspondence, accounts, lists, testimonies, questionnaires, certificates, petitions, card files, maps, circulars, graphs, protocols, and clippings relating to World War II, the Soviet occupation of Poland, the Polish-Soviet military and diplomatic agreements of 1941, the re-establishment of the Polish embassy in Moscow, Polish prisoners of war in the Soviet Union, deportations of Polish citizens to the Soviet Union, labor camps and settlements, relief work by the Polish social welfare department delegations among the deportees, the Polish armed forces formed in the Soviet Union, evacuation of Polish citizens to the Middle East, the Katyn massacre of Polish officers, and the breakdown of Polish-Soviet relations in 1943. Includes material on the Communist Party of the Soviet Union and the Soviet government, 1928-1929. A digital copy of this entire collection is available at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/35/0/-/.
Poland. Ambasada (Soviet Union) Records
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1945, with an increment received in 1959.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (79 reels).
A digital copy (digitized from microfilm by the Polish State Archives) is available in Poland's National Digital Archive at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/35/0/-/.
Related Collection(s)
Tadeusz Romer papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Wladyslaw Anders collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych records, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
Polish-Soviet diplomatic relations were severed with the Soviet occupation of Eastern Poland on September 17, 1939. After the German invasion of the USSR in June 1941, however, the Soviet government re-established diplomatic relations with the Polish government, then in exile in London. An agreement was signed on July 30, 1941, followed by a military accord on August 14. The Poles were allowed to re-establish an Embassy in Moscow, to form an army on Soviet territory for the common struggle against Germany, and to set up a network of Polish citizens deported to the USSR in 1939-1941.
Friction soon developed in several areas, leading to an eventual break in diplomatic relations. Of particular concern to the Polish government were the Polish deportees, many of whom were forced to accept Soviet rather than Polish citizenship. The activities of the Polish social welfare workers awoke the suspicions of the Soviet authorities, who conducted a series of arrests in June and July of 1942. Finally, the question of the fate of between 8,300 and 8,400 Polish officers who had been taken prisoner by the Soviet forces in 1939 and who were supposed to be released from the prison camps at Kozel'sk, Starobelsk and Ostashkov became a source of Polish-Soviet discord. The discovery by the Germans of mass graves of between 4,443 and 4,800 Polish officers at Katyn on April 13, 1943 seemed to confirm Polish suspicions. The Soviet authorities responded by accusing the Polish government of collaboration with the Germans. On April 25, 1943, the Soviet government broke diplomatic relations with the Polish government, and the mission of the Polish Embassy was officially terminated.
The Polish ambassador in Moscow from 1941 to July 5, 1942 was Stanislaw Kot. After the general evacuation, when the Embassy was moved to Kuibyshev, the post was assumed by Tadeusz Romer. He remained there until July 25, 1943, although his official status had been revoked in April of that year. The Romer papers are located at the Public Archives of Canada, and a microfilm copy has been deposited at the Hoover Institution.
A major part of the activity of the Polish Embassy was the organization of a network of social welfare "delegations" administered by "hommes de confiance" appointed by the Social Welfare Department. The Embassy representatives were responsible for the physical well-being, and in some cases the religious and educational care, of the more than one million Polish citizens deported by the Soviet authorities to labor camps and settlements in 1939-1941. A mass southward evacuation of these deportees was effected in 1943, and many made their way to Britain via Iran. A large number were interviewed in Tehran in 1943 regarding their experiences in the USSR. The interviews themselves are a part of the General Wladyslaw Anders Collection at the Hoover Institution.
Scope and Content of Collection
Reports, correspondence, accounts, lists, testimonies, questionnaires, certificates, petitions, card files, maps, circulars, graphs, protocols, and clippings relating to World War II, the Soviet occupation of Poland, the Polish-Soviet military and diplomatic agreements of 1941, the re-establishment of the Polish embassy in Moscow, Polish prisoners of war in the Soviet Union, deportations of Polish citizens to the Soviet Union, labor camps and settlements, relief work by the Polish social welfare department delegations among the deportees, the Polish armed forces formed in the Soviet Union, evacuation of Polish citizens to the Middle East, the Katyn massacre of Polish officers, and the breakdown of Polish-Soviet relations in 1943. Includes material on the Communist Party of the Soviet Union and the Soviet government, 1928-1929.
A digital copy of this entire collection is available at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/35/0/-/.
An item level inventory of the collection (in Polish) is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
Katyn Forest Massacre, 1940.; Poland--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Poland.; Poles--Soviet Union.; Prisoners of war.; Refugees.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Poland.; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1917-1936.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Conscript labor.; World War, 1939-1945--Deportations from Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945.
- ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE FILE, 1941-1943 (Boxes 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Circulars, instructions, orders, plans, and proposals, arranged by type of document.
  - General, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Circulars, instructions, and orders, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Instructions and orders, 1941-1943
  - Personnel records, 1941-1943
  - Plans and proposals, 1941-1943
  - Plans and proposals, 1941-1943 (Box 3)
- OFFICE FILE OF THE CONSULAR LEGAL DEPARTMENT, 1941-1944 (Boxes 3-19)
  Reports, lists, questionnaires, card files, and petitions, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General (Box 3)
  - Administration
  - Citizenship and passportization
    - General
    - Foreign citizenship
      - General
      - Czech (Box 4)
      - Soviet
      - United States
    - Polish citizenship
      - Questionnaires and lists
      - Questionnaires and lists
        - Polish passportization (Box 5)
        - Polish passportization (Box 6)
        - Soviet passportization
        - Registration
        - Registration (Box 7)
  - Deportations
    - General
    - Lists of deportees
      - General
      - As of December 30, 1942
    - Residence applications
  - Interventions
    - General
      - Arrests after amnesty (Box 8)
      - Courts, Soviet
      - Property (Box 9)
    - Correspondence
    - Lists
    - Reports (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous
  - Labor camps, settlements, and prisons
    - General
    - List
  - Legalizations
    - General
      - Certificates and lists (Box 11)
      - Extracts
    - Deaths
      - General
      - Card file (Boxes 12-13)
      - List (Box 14)
      - Notes (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous
  - Nationalities
    - General
    - Lists and petitions
    - Reports
      - Central European Federation
      - Eastern question
      - Internal affairs (Box 16)
      - Jews
  - Polskie Sily Zbrojne (PSZ) (Polish Armed Forces)
    - General
    - Berling, Colonel Zygmunt, Polish military units formed by under Soviet authorities, report, 1944 June 5
    - Financial and personnel matters
    - Griazovets camp, prisoners of war and internees (as of August 3, 1941) at, list (Box 17)
    - Kalwaria camp (Lithuania), officers interned at
    - Koltubanka and Totskoe labor camps (Orenburg, formerly Chkalov, region), Polish citizens at
    - Prisoners of war, missing (Kozel'sk, Starobelsk and Ostashkov camps), list, 1941 December
    - Railway workers, 1941-1942
    - Red Army, Poles in
    - Service, military (Box 18)
      - Laws on universal military service obligation
      - Release and deferment, etc.
    - Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR), official relations with
    - Women volunteers, questionnaires
    - Miscellaneous contracts, lists, correspondence, etc. (Box 19)
  - Prisoners of war
    - General
    - Lists
  - Searches
  - Visas
- OFFICE FILE OF THE FINANCIAL DEPARTMENT, 1941-1944 (Box 19)
  Reports, accounts, and inventory, arranged alphabetically by type of document.
  - General (Box 19)
    - Biurobin (Foreigners' Service Office) accounts, 1941-1944
    - Informational materials
  - Budget
  - Inventory
  - Reports
    - 1941 August 7 - 1943 May 12
    - 1943 January 1
- OFFICE FILE OF THE POLITICAL-INFORMATIONAL DEPARTMENT, 1928-1943 (Boxes 19-24)
  Correspondence, reports, protocols, lists, and clippings, arranged alphabetically by type of document.
  - General
    - Matusinski affair (Box 19)
    - Polish-Soviet Agreement, 1941 (Box 20)
    - Press and radio
    - Sikorski, General Wladyslaw, visit of
    - USSR
      - Antisemitism, report
      - Officials (party and government)
        - Comintern, report and lists, 1928
        - Communist Party of the Soviet Union Central Committee, list, 1928(?)
        - Government, Council of People's Commissars, list, 1928(?)
        - Government, Party, and Comintern, table, 1928(?)
  - Circulars (Box 21)
  - Clippings
    - Polish-Soviet Declaration of Friendship and Mutual Aid, signing of, 1941
    - Various
  - Correspondence, 1941-1943
    - Indices of correspondence
    - General
      - 1941 September 9 - 1942 December 31
      - 1941-1942
      - Courier post (Box 22)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych (Ministry of Foreign Affairs), 1941-1942
    - Narodnyi komissariat po inostrannym delam (NKID) (People's Commissariat of Foreign Affairs)
      - Received
      - Sent
        - 1942 January 3 - 1942 December 30
        - 1942 January 8 - 1943 April 26 (Box 23)
        - 1943 January 8 - 1943 April 20
  - Newspaper issue, Pravda, 1929 March 3
  - Notes received by the Ambassador, Kuibyshev, 1942
  - Protocols, 1941-1943
    - Conversations with NKID, folder 1
    - Conversations with NKID, folder 3
    - Conversations with NKID, folder 4
  - Reports received from and sent to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1941-1942 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous
- OFFICE FILE OF THE SOCIAL WELFARE DEPARTMENT, 1941-1944 (Boxes 24-52)
  Reports, testimonies, protocols, lists, certificates, card files, questionnaires, and photographs, arranged alphabetically by type of document.
  - Subject file
    - Children
      - Culture and education (Box 24)
      - Deportation and life in USSR
      - Evacuation (Box 25)
    - Delegations, Embassy Social Welfare Department
      - Arkhangel'sk region
        - Arkhangel'sk
        - Arkhangel'sk (Box 26)
        - Kotlas
      - Arkhangel'sk and Vologda regions
      - European Russia (Box 27)
      - Kazakh Soviet Socialist Republic
        - General (Box 28)
        - Dzhambul
      - Kirov, Molotov, and Krasnoiarsk
      - Krasnoiarsk Territory (Box 29)
      - Novosibirsk and Altai regions
      - Primor'e (Maritime Territory), Vladivostok
        - General
        - Calendar of documents
        - Correspondence (Box 30)
        - Lists, prisoners of war
        - Notebooks
        - Notebooks (Box 31)
      - Siberia
      - Uzbek Soviet Socialist Republic, Samarkand, Tashkent, etc.
      - General
      - General (Box 32)
    - Deportations
      - General (Box 33)
      - History (Box 34)
    - Discipline
    - Finances
      - General
      - Allowances for individuals
      - Budget Commission
      - Budget, monthly (Box 35)
      - Grants-in-aid
      - Individual aid
    - Legal affairs
    - Liquidation of delegations
    - Personnel (Box 36)
      - Applications for employment
      - Arrests, 1942
      - Deportation and evacuation from USSR, 1942
    - Red Cross
    - Religious life of Polish citizens in USSR
    - Soldiers' families (Box 37)
      - Aid
      - Evacuation
    - Stroibatal'iony (Construction Battalions) and Red Army, Polish citizens in
    - Stroibatal'iony (Construction Battalions) and Red Army, Polish citizens in (Box 38)
    - Miscellaneous
  - Card files, Embassy social welfare representatives and delegations (Boxes 39-40)
  - Certificates (Box 41)
    - 1941-1942
    - 1942
  - Correspondence, 1941-1942
  - Graphs
  - Lists
    - Children and orphans, numbers and distribution of (as of April 25, 1943)
    - Deportees, numbers and distribution of
    - Evacuees
    - Social welfare establishments
      - As of December 1, 1942
      - As of February 15, 1943
      - As of February 16, 1943
  - Notes on telephone conversations, 1941-1943 (Box 42)
  - Photographs, women deportees, Komi A.S.S.R.
    - Letka region
    - Syktyvkar region
  - Questionnaires, religious life of Polish citizens in USSR
  - Registers
    - Children, transport of
    - Social welfare establishments (Box 43)
    - Social welfare establishments (Box 44)
  - Reports
    - General
      - 1941-1943
      - 1941 November 1 - 1943 February 15
      - 1942 December
      - 1942-1943
      - 1943 March 16
    - Calculation of number of deportees, 1943 June 14
    - Deportees, conditions of life of
      - North and Central European Russia (Kuibyshev), 1943 April 10
      - Ural region-Chelabinsk and Sverdlovsk regions
      - Uzbek and Turkmen SSR
      - Fergana Valley, Surkhandar'ia region and Stalinabad
      - Karaganda, Akmolinsk and Kustanai regions (Kuibyshev), 1943 August 30
      - Kazakh SSR, 1943 April 3 (Box 45)
      - Kirghiz and South and Central Kazakh SSR, 1943 March
    - Finances
    - "Individual Aid from the Polish Embassy in the USSR for Polish Citizens" (Tehran), 1943 July 17
    - Liquidation of delegations, 1942 October 30
    - Relief from abroad
    - Religious life and clergy, 1943 August 14
    - Social welfare representatives, Ural region, evaluations of
    - Transport and supply
      - General
      - "Soviet Allotments of Food and Manufactured Goods for the Polish Population and the Welfare Establishments" (Tehran), 1943 July 28
      - Transport Department
  - Testimonies
    - Adults
      - Bialystok Province (Box 46)
      - Lwow Province
      - Nowogrod Province
      - Polesie Province (Box 47)
      - Stanislawow Province
      - Tarnopol Province
      - Wolyn Province
      - Wolyn Province (Box 48)
      - Various
    - Children
      - Bialystok Province (Box 49)
      - Lwow Province
      - Nowogrodek Province
      - Polesie Province
      - Stanislawow Province
      - Tarnopol Province
      - Warsaw Province (Box 50)
      - Wilno Province
      - Wolyn Province
      - Various delegations
  - Testimonies and protocols of the Investigative Commission of the Polish Ministry of Justice, Tehran, 1943-1944
    - Akmolinsk delegation (Box 51)
    - Alma-Ata delegation
    - Ashkhabad delegation
    - Barnaul delegation
    - Chelabinsk delegation
    - Chimkent delegation
    - Chkalov (now Orenburg) delegation
    - Dzhambul delegation
    - Kirov delegation
    - Krasnoiarsk delegation
    - Kustanai delegation
    - Pavlodar delegation
    - Petropavlovsk delegation
    - Samarkand delegation
    - Semipalatinsk delegation
    - Syktyvkar delegation (Box 52)
    - Various delegations
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1941-1943 (Boxes 52-54)
  Official correspondence of the Polish Embassy in Moscow and Kuibyshev, including correspondence of Ambassadors Stanislaw Kot and Tadeusz Romer, arranged alphabetically by name of principal correspondent and preceded by registers of correspondence for August 1941 through December 1942.
  - Registers of correspondence (Box 52)
    - 1941 August 19 - 1941 December 31
    - 1942 January 1 - 1942 July 17
    - 1942 July 17 - 1942 December 31
  - Kot, Ambassador Stanislaw, official correspondence, Moscow, 1941-1942 (Box 53)
  - Ministerstwo Pracy i Opieky (Ministry of Labour and Social Welfare), London, correspondence with, Kuibyshev, 1942-1943
  - Narodnyi komissariat po inostrannykh delam (NKID) (People's Commissariat of Foreign Affairs), correspondence with, Kuibyshev, 1942
    - Letters sent
    - Letters received
  - Romer, Ambassador Tadeusz, official correspondence, Kuibyshev, 1942-1943
    - Letters sent and received, 1942
    - Letters received, 1942-1943
  - Various correspondence (Box 54)
    - 1942
    - 1942-1943
- MAPS, undated (Box 54)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Deportations of Polish Citizens from Territories Occupied by the Soviet Union from 1939-1941" (Box 54)
  - "Distribution of Polish Citizens Released by the Soviet Authorities after the Conclusion of the Polish-Soviet Agreement of the July 30th [sic] 1941"
  - "Mapa Specjalna Rozmieszczenia Ludnosci Polskiej w Z.S.S.R." ("Special Map of the Distribution of the Polish Population in the U.S.S.R.")
  - "Settlements of Polish Citizens Deported from Poland by the Soviet Union during the Period 1939-1941"
  - "Soviet Empire in Europe and Asia"
- MISCELLANY, undated (Box 54)
- UNSORTED MATERIAL, undated (Boxes 55-58)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL, undated (Map case)
  Original, hand-made map of Soviet forced labor camps and prisons from which Polish citizens were released between 1941 and 1943.
- DECLASSIFIED U.S. GOVERNMENT RECORDS, 1941-1942 (Box 58)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some interfiled, unclassified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, then chronologically thereunder by date of creation.
  - 2016 January release of records, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 58: 6)
    Consists of the following:
    Statement by the Polish government, in French, 7 July 1941 [originally in box 20].
    List, "Stores for the Polish Forces - Arriving in Russia in Convoy P.Q.1," 29 September 1941 [originally in box 38].
    Letter from Monsieur L. Baggallay, H.Ms British Embassy, regarding Latvians deported to Russia, 4 February 1942 [originally in box 21].
    Telegram from British Military Mission, Moscow, 19 March [1942] and Aide Memoire from the British Military Mission attaching "Notes by British Chiefs of Staff Regarding the Polish Forces in Russia," 28 November 1941 [originally in box 16].
    Statement regarding Polish-Soviet relations, in French, 27 July 1942 [two copies, one originally in box 3, the other originally in box 36].